Brockway Family Papers
Brockway family Papers
1805-1962
Brockway family.
1 linear ft.
Papers of the members of the Brockway family (of Central New York State, Syracuse, N.Y, and Fulton County, N.Y.). The collection consists of correspondence (largely incoming, to various family members), account books, church records, diaries, financial and legal papers, and memorabilia.
148867
Biographical History
Tiffany Brockway (1774-1866) brought his family -- including his father, Nathan (1736-1822) -- from Rensselaer County to the central New York area, near what would become Broadalbin, in 1791. The unusual appellation had been Nathan's mother Elizabeth's maiden name; Nathan also had a brother named Tiffany Brockway (b. 1740).
In 1805 Tiffany Brockway and his first wife, Lucy Alvord (1778-1819), settled on a nearby farm called Locust Grove and eventually produced four daughters and two sons. He served as a major in the War of 1812 and for many years as a colonel in the local militia. Colonel Brockway was the first outspoken abolitionist in Broadalbin, and his home at Locust Grove was a known stop on the Underground Railroad that sheltered and assisted fugitive slaves. Brockway and his second wife, Mary G. Owen, had no children, but one of his sons by Lucy Alvord, Tiffany Brockway, Jr. (b. 1813), inherited the farm at Broadalbin.
Members of the Brockway Family were associated with Central New York State, Syracuse, N.Y, and Fulton County, N.Y.
[Portions of this biographical sketch obtained from "Obituaries and Biographies of Broadalbin," compiled by Dave Bixby and available online at http://fulton.nygenweb.net/bios/DBobitsBR.html.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Brockway Family Papers consist of biographical material, correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, and published material relating to Colonel Tiffany Brockway, his father Nathan, son Tiffany Jr., and various other family members.
Biographical material includes genealogy notes and biographical sketches of various family members. Correspondence, largely incoming, contains letters to and from various family members, a letter about the family, and transcripts of letters. Subject files include account books, church records, diaries, financial papers, land surveys, legal agreements, newspaper clippings, photographs, settlement of estate, a speech, and unidentified miscellanea. The single item in Manuscripts is a speech by Tiffany Brockway, Jr. Published material contains a hymn by Helen Hale Brockway and a notice.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Brockway, Mary G.; Brockway, Tiffany.; Brockway family.; Genealogy.; Broadalbin (N.Y.) -- History.; New York (State) -- History.; Syracuse (N.Y.) -- History.; Account books.; Biographies.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Genealogies (histories); Photographs.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Frederick Fuhrer and Anna B. Easton, 1962.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Brockway genealogy notes (Box 1)
  - Biographical sketches
    - Brockway, Charles Tiffany (Box 1)
    - Brockway, Emma Hale (Box 1)
    - Brockway, Nathan (Box 1)
    - Brockway, Tiffany (Box 1)
    - Easton, Anna Brockway (Box 1)
    - Easton, James Irwin (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - Babcock, Cornelia A., See Brockway, Cornelia A.
    - Brockway, Cornelia A., 1835-1836 (Box 1)
    - Brockway, Helen Hale, 1918 (Box 1)
    - Brockway, Mary G.
      - Barlowe, 1815 (Box 1)
      - Chase, Fanny, 1814 (Box 1)
      - G---, 1808 (Box 1)
      - Hallett, Mollie, 1864 (Box 1)
      - Matthews, John, 1858; 1864 (Box 1)
      - Owen, Emeline, See Owen, George W.
      - Owen, Francis R., See Owen, George W.
      - Owen, George W., 1829-1838; 1841-1864; 12 folders (Box 1)
      - Owen, John H., 1856; 1862-1863 (Box 1)
      - Owen, Marana (Box 1)
      - Owen, Mary, 1852; 1861,; 1864,; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
        See also Owen, John H.
      - Post, Justus, 1806 (Box 1)
      - Seeber, John, 1817 (Box 1)
      - Smith, Abild, 1835 (Box 1)
      - Smith, John, 1830; 1833-1834 (Box 1)
      - Smith, Lucius, 1842-1847; 1850-1858; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Smith, Sidney, 1830; 1834,; 1839 (Box 1)
      - Webber, Christopher, [1809?] (Box 1)
      - Wells, Sarah L., 1863 (Box 1)
      - Unidentified (Box 1)
    - Brockway, Tiffany
      - Smith, John, 1829-1830; 1834 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1869; photocopies (Box 1)
    - Brockway, Tiffany Jr. (Box 1)
    - Fergason, Peter, 1838; photocopies (Box 1)
    - Gordon, P.R., 1861; photocopies (Box 1)
    - Owen, George W., 1863 (Box 1)
    - Owen, Mary G., See Brockway, Mary G.
    - Owen, Stephen, undated (Box 1)
    - Smith, John
      - Lord, Benjamin, 1813 (Box 1)
    - Smith, Lucius
      - Brockway, Mary, 1856 (Box 1)
      - Owen, George W., See Brockway, Mary G.
      - Smith, Marana, 1847 (Box 1)
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 1)
    - Smith, Mary, See Brockway, Mary G.
    - Wilson, Maria
      - Wilson, Charles, 1832 (Box 1)
  - Transcripts from various family members (Box 1)
  - Correspondence by others, concerning Brockway family, 1892; photocopy (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Account book (Tiffany Brockway, Jr.), 1838-1866 (Oversze 1)
  - Account book (unidentified), 1842-1845 (Oversze 1)
  - Church records (Tiffany Brockway), 1835; 1868,; undated; some photocopies (Box 1)
  - Commission (Tiffany Brockway, Jr.), 1838; photocopy (Box 1)
  - Diaries
    - Charles T. Brockway, 1856; photocopy (Box 1)
    - Nathan Brockway, 1832; photocopy (Box 1)
    - Tiffany Brockway, "An account of Tiffany Brockway's travel from New York to settle the estate of his brother in Ohio", 1837; includes transcription (Box 2)
    - Unidentified, 1865; photocopy (Box 2)
  - Financial papers
    - Charles Brockway, 1809; photocopy (Box 2)
    - Mary G. Brockway, 1866 (Box 2)
    - Nathan Brockway, 1805-1814; photocopy (Box 2)
    - Tiffany Brockway, 1807; 1809-1812,; 1815,; 1817,; 1839,; 1848,; 1859,; 1862,; 1864; photocopies (Box 2)
    - Tiffany Brockway Jr., 1828; 1839-1840,; 1861,; 1865; mostly photocopies (Box 2)
      See also Tiffany Brockway, above.
    - Gilbert Fergason, 1822 (Box 2)
    - Jos Ferguson, 1852; photocopy (Box 2)
    - Unidentified, 1808; 1866,; undated; photocopies (Box 2)
  - Inventory (George W. Owen), 1865 (Box 2)
  - Land surveys (Tiffany Brockway), 1854; 1861,; undated; includes some photocopies (Box 2)
  - Legal agreements
    - Elizabeth Brockway, 1861; 1866; photocopies (Box 2)
    - Tiffany Brockway, 1823; 1838,; 1848-1849; includes some photocopies (Box 2)
    - Tiffany Brockway Jr., See Tiffany Brockway, above.
  - Newspaper clippings
    - Charles T. Brockway, 1922; 1962; photocopies (Box 2)
    - Helen Hale Brockway, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Charles T. Brockway (Box 2)
    - Cornelia Ann Brockway (Box 2)
    - Tiffany Brockway (Box 2)
    - Tiffany Brockway Jr. (Box 2)
    - Charles Brockway Hale, See Family of Charles Tiffany Brockway, below.
    - Jean Brockway Hale, See Family of Charles Tiffany Brockway, below.
    - Ruth Hubbell (Box 2)
    - Family of Charles Tiffany Brockway (Box 2)
    - Family of Tiffany Brockway Jr. (Box 2)
    - Home, Locust Grove, Broadalbin [Township, New York] (Box 2)
  - Prescription, unidentified, photocopy (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks, See Subject files: Account book (Tiffany Brockway, Jr.) and Subject files: Account book (unidentified).
  - Settlement of Estate (Nathan Brockway), 1838; undated; photocopy (Box 2)
  - Speech (Tiffany Brockway Jr.), 1887; transcribed copy (Box 2)
  - Stock certificate (Tiffany Brockway), 1813; photocopy (Box 2)
  - Ticket, Central Park Carriage Service, undated; photocopy (Box 2)
  - Unidentified, photocopies (Box 2)
- Manuscripts
  - Speech (Tiffany Brockway Jr.), 1887 (Box 2)
- Published material
  - "Hymn to Crouse Irving" (Helen Hale Brockway), undated (Box 2)
  - Notice, "The Two Roads to Peace", circa 1865 (Box 2)